Finding Aid for Ivan F. Duff papers, 1947-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ivan F. Duff papers
1947-1994
1976-1982
Duff, Ivan F. (1915-1994)
95106 Aa 2
Rheumatologist and founder of the University of Michigan Turner Geriatric Clinic; director of the Rackham Arthritis Research Unit and chief of the Arthritis Division. Records relating to the development of gerontological medicine at the University of Michigan and the founding of the Turner Geriatric Clinic; includes biographical material, correspondence, planning records, name files, and topical files relating to gerontology and rheumatic diseases.
4.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were received in 1994 (Donor No. 4713 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ivan Francis Duff, professor, rheumatologist, and founder of the Turner Geriatric Clinic at the University of Michigan, was born in Pendleton, Oregon, on July 20, 1915. He graduated from Pendleton High School and attended the University of Oregon, receiving a bachelor's degree in 1938. He enrolled in the University of Michigan Medical School, earning his medical degree in 1940, and completing his internship and residency training in internal medicine.
Following service with the Navy during World War II, he returned to Ann Arbor in 1946 and joined the Department of Internal Medicine as an instructor and helped to develop the Anticoagulation Clinic. Rheumatology was his primary interest, and in 1953 he was promoted to associate professor and placed in charge of the Rackham Arthritis Research Unit. He was promoted to the rank of professor in 1960.
During the 1960s he took part in several epidemiologic investigations of rheumatic diseases, including the School of Public Health's Community Health Study at Tecumseh, Michigan, under the direction of Thomas Francis. In 1964 he began a lengthy association with the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission (ABCC), studying the occurrence of rheumatoid arthritis among the populations of Hiroshima and Nagasaki, Japan. His studies extended to research on rheumatic diseases throughout the Far East, including Australia, China, Malaysia, Nepal, New Zealand, and the Philippines.
In 1969, he became chief of the University of Michigan Arthritis Division and served as director of the Regional Arthritis Control Program from 1969 to 1971. He directed the Pilot Geriatric Arthritis Center from 1974 until 1977, when he was asked to establish a comprehensive health care program focusing on the special needs of the elderly. The program became the Turner Geriatric Clinic which he directed from 1977 to 1980. From 1980 to 1984, he was acting chief of the newly created Division of Geriatric Medicine. In 1986 he was awarded emeritus status by the university, and continued to see patients until shortly before his death.
Active within his profession, he was a founding member of the National Society of Rheumatologists. He was also active in the American College of Rheumatology, American Rheumatism Society, Michigan Rheumatism Society, and the Michigan Arthritis Foundation. He chaired the Arthritis Foundation Government Liaison Committee from 1973 to 1979, and helped draft legislation which resulted in the passage of the National Arthritis Act.
Dr. Duff died October 27, 1994 at the age of 79. He was survived by his wife of 52 years, the former Betty Anne Macduff, and two sons, David Bruce and Frank Nelson.
The Ivan Duff papers consist of four and one-half linear feet of records dating from 1947 to 1994, although the bulk of the coverage is from the 1970s. The strength of the collection is the documentation of the development of gerontological medicine at the University of Michigan, particularly the founding of the Turner Geriatric Clinic in 1977. There is very little in this collection, however, relating to Duff's prior activities or to the Rackham Arthritis Research Unit which he directed from 1953 until 1969 (for information on this unit researchers should consult the separate record groups, Rackham Arthritis Unit and the University of Michigan Department of Internal Medicine).
Subjects:
Older people--Diseases.; Older people--Dwellings.; Duff, Ivan Francis, 1915-; Geriatrics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gerontology--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; National Society of Clinical Rheumatologists.; Turner Geriatric Clinic.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Internal Medicine.; University of Michigan. Division of Geriatrics.; University of Michigan. Division of Gerontology.
- Biographical/Personal Material
  The Biographical/Personal Material series is an artificial grouping of files dating from 1947 to 1991. It consists of family correspondence and personnel related files, including his curricula vitae, sabbatical records, lecture notes (1964-1972), and assorted photographs.
  - Biographical, 1947-1985 (Box 1)
  - Employment Opportunities, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
  - Family Correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Gray, Nina Duff, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Lecture Notes, 1964-1972 (Box 1)
  - Sabbaticals, 1957; 1964-1967; 1983-1984; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1950-1991 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Tenure, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Retirement, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
- Geriatric Programs
  The Geriatric Programs series, 1973-1991, is comprised of files documenting the development and implementation of geriatric medicine programs, including the Pilot Geriatric Arthritis Center, the Turner Geriatric Clinic, and the Division of Geriatric Medicine. Files include planning documents, reports, partial minutes and correspondence. The Pilot Geriatric Arthritis Center files contain the original 1974 grant application that funded the Center, and material evaluating the Center's effectiveness. The Turner Geriatric Clinic records are the most substantial, indicative of Dr. Duff's major role in establishing the Clinic. Records include background on the Scott and Amy Prudden Turner bequest, concept papers, meeting files, and information on outreach activities, including satellite clinics. The Division of Geriatric Medicine records consist of proposals to develop a division of geriatric medicine and annual progress reports from 1980 to 1984.
  - Pilot Geriatric Arthritis Center
    - Application, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Outreach Project, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Outreach Project Final Evaluation, 1978-1983 (Box 1)
    - Quarterly Reports, 1974-1977; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Turner Geriatric Clinic
    - Turner Bequest, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Concept Paper Gerontological Health Care, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Inpatient Beds, 1974-1978 (Box 1)
    - Letters of Agreement, Space Issues, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
    - Phase I, 1976-1977; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Professional Services Work Group, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Program Meetings
      - Central Campus, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Medical Campus, 1976-1979; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Psychiatry, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
    - Social Work Program, 1982; 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Turner Clinic Information, 1979-1984 (Box 1)
    - Turner Community Advisory Committee, 1979-1985; 3 folders (Box 1)
      (includes scattered minutes)
    - Turner Minority Access Subcommittee, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Turner Outreach Program Reports, 1982-1984 (Box 2)
    - Turner Satellite Clinics
      - General, 1980-1984 (Box 2)
      - Fourmidable Group, 1980-1984 (Box 2)
      - Mobile Turner Clinic Program, 1982-1984 (Box 2)
      - Tenant Questionnaire, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Satellite Clinics
        - Baker Commons Senior Housing, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
        - Brookhaven Manor, 1989 (Box 2)
        - Clark Towers, 1984 (Box 2)
        - Cranbrook Tower, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
        - Glacier Hills Nursing Center, 1980 (Box 2)
        - Parkway Meadows, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Division of Geriatric Medicine
    - Proposals, 1977-1981 (Box 2)
    - Annual Progress Reports
      - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Multidisciplinary Geriatric Medicine Training Program, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Noon Departmental Conferences, 1982-1984 (Box 2)
- Name Files
  The series Name Files is comprised of alphabetically arranged correspondence files with University of Michigan figures, gerontologists, rheumatologists, physicians, and foreign visitors. The files date from 1971 to 1994, although the majority of the material dates from 1975 to 1980. Several of the files relate to the Turner Geriatric Clinic, including three folders of correspondence and memos to and from William N. Kelley, head of the University of Michigan Department of Internal Medicine which had oversight for the Turner Clinic.
  - Becker, Marjorie, 1971-1983 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Benedict, Robert C., 1978 (Box 2)
  - Bethune, Norman, 1978-1985 (Box 2)
  - Butler, Robert N., 1977 (Box 2)
  - Cohen, Wilbur, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Cole, Theodore, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Curran, Suzanne, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Deniston, O. Lynn, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Engleman, Ephraim, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Goddard, Katherine Russell, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - Hansen, Barbara, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Huang, Ding-jiu, 1981-1984; 1990; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Hubbard, William N, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Johnson, Harold, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Jun-di, Pan, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Kelley, William N, 1976-1982; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Martell, William, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Moseman, Anne, 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Payne, Beverly, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Pettinger, Wilbur B., 1980 (Box 2)
  - Plotz, Charles, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Power, Eugene, 1981-1982; 1990; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Power, Sarah Goddard, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Radock, Michael, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Robinson, William D., 1992 (Box 2)
  - Santinga, John, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Smythe, Charley, 1973-1994 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Stearns, Eugene, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Steele, Knight, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Vernoff, Samuel, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Wittenborg, Harriet, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Zander, Alvin, 1975-1980 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series dates from 1959 to 1993 and includes files relating mainly to gerontological issues and programs. As with the Name Files, there is some overlap with the Turner Clinic and the Division of Geriatric Medicine, primarily in the fundraising files. Of interest are the National Society of Clinical Rheumatologists files which document Dr. Duff's role as a founding member of this organization. A number of Ann Arbor area organizations and programs for senior citizens are also documented here (i.e., Domino's House and Housing Bureau for Seniors).
  - Ad Hoc Committee of Community Agencies, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Alzheimer's Disease, 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - American Board of Internal Medicine, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Art Work (in Clinic Space), 1979; 1992 (Box 2)
  - Arthritis Disease Control Programs, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Assisted Suicide, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission, Taiwan, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - China Trips, 1972-1974; 1980; 1981-1982; 1983; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Congressional Geriatric Bills, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Continence Program, 1981-1984 (Box 3)
  - Continuing Medical Education in Geriatrics, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Critical Clinical Issues in the Care of the Elderly, 1980-1983; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Cross Sectional Serum Uric Acid, Cholesterol and Rheumatoid Factor Values from Persons of Varying Locale and Ethnic Background, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Didactic/Experimental Program for Memory Strengthening, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Dieticians, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
  - Divorce After 60, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Domino's House
    - General, 1987-1991 (Box 3)
    - Newsletter, 1988-1993 (Box 3)
  - Duke University Center for the Study of Aging and Human Development, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Elder Care, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Epidemiology of Rheumatoid Arthritis and Gout in Japan and China, 1982 (Box 3)
  - "For Men Only,", 1982 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising and Foundations
    - General, 1976-1985 (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor Area Foundation, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Area Agency on Aging, 1977-1978; 1983; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Commonwealth Fund, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Josiah Macy, Jr. Foundation, 1978; 1981 (Box 3)
    - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
      - Proposal, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Proposal, 1981; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - W.K. Kellogg Foundation, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Fulbright-Hays Programme, University of Otago, New Zea, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Geriatrics Center, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
  - Geriatric Day Hospital, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Geriatric Medicine Referral Service, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Gerontology Curriculum Development, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Health Screening for the Elderly, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Housing Bureau for Seniors
    - General, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Minutes, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Houston Academy of Medicine, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Japan Trips, 1966-1969; 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Jewish Institute for Geriatric Care, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Kellogg International Scholarship Program in Health and Aging, 1980-1984 (Box 4)
  - Lafayette Clinic (Detroit, MI), 1980 (Box 4)
  - Lifeline Systems Inc., 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Life Review Project, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Long Term Nursing Home Care Insurance in Michigan, circa 1987 (Box 4)
  - "The Medical Problems of Aging,", 1984 (Box 4)
  - MESA (Medical Epidemiologic Aspects of Aging), 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Association of Nursing Home Community Councils, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Michigan White House Conference on Aging, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Multidisciplinary Geriatric Education Center, 1983 (Box 4)
  - National Advisory Council on Geriatric Medical Programs, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - National Arthritis Center Community Service Development Component, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - National Cancer Institute Grant, 1983 (Box 4)
  - National Society of Clinical Rheumatologists, 1959-1989; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Needs Assessment for Elderly in Washtenaw County, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Nurse Practitioner, 1972-1978 (Box 4)
  - Ophthalmology Service, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Organic Brain Disease, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Palliative Care Consultation Service, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Pan American Congress of Rheumatology, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Peer Counselors, 1981-1984 (Box 4)
  - Philadelphia Geriatric Center, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Physician Activity Reports, 1979-1984 (Box 4)
  - Publicity, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Rackham Arthritis Research Unit, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Radio Talk on Turner Clinic, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Residencies and Fellowships
    - Geriatric Fellowship, 1980-1984 (Box 4)
    - Resident in Geriatrics, 1980-1984 (Box 4)
    - Resident in Family Practice, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
    - Veterans Administration
      - Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
      - Residency and Fellowship Program, 1979-1982 (Box 4)
  - Regional Medical Program of Hawaii, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Rensis Likert and Associates, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Rheumatology Exchange Group (China Tour), 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Saline Community Hospital, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Tecumseh X-rays, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Triage Incorporated, 1977 (Box 5)
  - XII International Congress of Rheumatology, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Veterans Administration Hospital
    - Hospital Based Home Care Program, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Vital Signs Seminar, "Leading the Way in Geriatrics,", September 25, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw County Health Questionnaire, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw United Way, 1981-1983 (Box 5)
  - WHO/ILAR Joint Programme on Rheumatic Diseases Prevention and Control, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Ypsilanti Regional Psychiatric Hospital, 1984 (Box 5)
- Publications, 1947-1984
  The Publications series includes scattered reprints and manuscripts of published articles, 1947-1984.
  - Reprints, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts of writings, 2 folders (Box 5)
Related Material
Most records relating to Dr. Duff's affiliation with the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission (ABCC) are housed at the Historical Research Center of the Houston Academy of Medicine-Texas Medical Center Library in Houston, Texas along with the records of others involved with ABCC studies.
The Marjorie Brazer collection includes an oral history interview with Ivan Duff.